Guide to the Mark Arthur May papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Mark Arthur May papers
1911-1978
MS 1447
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.5
(16 boxes)
The collection contains correspondence, research files, writings, and photographs documenting the professional life of Mark Arthur May, educational psychologist.
May, Mark A. (Mark Arthur), 1891-1977
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William W. May, 1986.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Mark Arthur May was an educational psychologist whose long career encompassed teaching, research, and administrative responsibilities. He was born on August 12, 1891 in Jonesboro, Tennessee. In 1911, he received an A.B. from Maryville College in Tennessee and, in 1912, he earned a Ph.B. at the University of Chicago. Following a period in which he pursued ministerial studies at the Union Theological Seminary, May entered Columbia University and earned a Ph.D. in psychology in 1917. During WorldWar I, May served in the United States Army and administered the Army's mental testing program.
In 1919, May accepted a professorship in psychology at Syracuse University where he became one of the key figures in the development of the psychology department. Thereafter, a collaborative projecton-themoralbehavior of children called the Character Education Inquiry, which May undertook as a research associate at Columbia University from 1924-1926, brought him greater recognition within the discipline. The Inquiry led to highly regarded published work on the nature ofmoral behavior among school children.
In 1927, May accepted a full professorship in educational psychology at Yale University, where he remained until he retired in 1960. Soon after his arrival at Yale, May became executive secretary and then director (1935-1961) ofthe University's Institute ofHuman Relations (IHR), work for which he became well known. The IHR was first organized in 1929 to further develop and integrate teaching and learning at Yale that pertained to the study of man. Under May's leadership, the Institute concentrated on developing a "base science ofhuman behavior and social life." In doing so, the Institute made important contributions to understanding juvenile delinquency, psychotherapy, cultural conflicts, child rearing, and education.
In addition to working for Yale, May was a scientific consultant to the War Department during World War II on matters ofpsychological warfare and the psychological effects ofweaponry. After the war, he was a member of the Advisory Commission on Information to the United States Information Agency (USIA) and became the Commission's chairman in 1952. The Commission was comprised ofpresidentialappointees. In its role as an independent oversight committee, it observed and assessed USIA information programs at home and abroad and reported its findings to Congress on a regular basis. May made several trips abroad as part ofhis work for the Commission, during which he developed and made use ofhis expertise in propaganda and propaganda techniques. May's life-long interest in films and their educational uses led him to chair the Teaching Films Custodians (TFC) from 1946 to 1958. TFC was a cooperative venture that combined the talents of educators and motion picture experts in the development of classroom films.
May was a productive and respected scholar who published a number of works during his career. Among the more notable are Education in the World of Fear (1941), A Social Psychology of War and Peace (1943), and Learning from Films (1957). He was a fellow of both the American Psychological Association and the American Academy of Arts and Sciences. He was also a member of the National Academy of Education.
May married Ruby Charles in 1917. They had two children: Samuel Cassamere and Martha Norwood. May died in Manchester, New Hampshire on January 2, 1977.
Scope and Contents
The papers are arranged in five series: Correspondence; Professional; Research and Work; Writings; and Photographs. The materials document the professional life of Mark May. May's interest in human behavior and concomitant research is evident throughout the collection. His career-long interest in education, especially character education and the use of films in the classroom is well documented, as is his service on the United States Advisory Commission on Information. There are also materials from his work for the armed forces during the two world wars. There is limited, but interesting, documentation of May's tenure at the Institute of Human Relations (IHR). For additional material on the IHR, researchers should consult YRG 37 Yale University Institute of Human Relations Records.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in five series: I. Correspondence, 1918-1970. II. Professional Files, 1914-1978. III. Research and Work, 1918-1965. IV. Writings, 1911-1971. V. Photographs, n.d.
Educational psychology; Learning ability; Learning ability -- Testing; Moral education; Moral education (Early childhood); Moral education (Elementary); Moral education (Higher); Moral education (Secondary); Personality; Personality assessment; Personality questionnaires; Propaganda; Psychology -- Study and teaching; Teaching -- Aids and devices; May, Mark A. (Mark Arthur), 1891-1977; Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.); United States Information Agency; Yale University. Department of Psychology; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Institute of Human Relations; Yale University. Institute of Human Relations. Monday Night Group
- Correspondence, 1918-1970; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The correspondence series is divided into two sections: General and Select. Both sections primarily contain professional correspondence and are arranged alphabetically. In each, letters to and from May are kept in the same folder under the name of the individual or institution with which Maycorresponded. Foldersmayhold letters to or from a third party, but all such letters bear somerelationto the primary individual or institution named. The letters collected in the General section mostly document' professional affiliations of a short-lived nature and routine matters. The Select correspondence documents the more substantial professional relationships which May developed overthe course ofhiscareer, bothwithindividuals and institutions, but many of these letters are also of a routine nature. There is correspondence of brief and conventional nature with a few well-known scholars ofhis day.
  - General
    - B, 1936-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - C, 1926-1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - D-E, 1934-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - F, 1929-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - G, 1939-1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hagen -Hawaii, 1924-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Healey-Hutch, 1924-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - I, 1930-1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - K-L-M, 1929-1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Lectures [correspondence regarding]
      - Accepted, 1932-1958 (Box 2, Folder 40097)
      - Rejected, 1934-1956 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - P-Q-R, 1932-1960 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - S, 1925-1960 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - T, 1928-1957 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - W, 1935-1939 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Select
    - Allport, Gordon, 1936-1947 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Buxton, Claude, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Cantril, Hadley [senior counsellor, The Institute for International Social Research, Princeton University], 1940-1955 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Character Education Inquiry, 1927-1953 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Cross, Wilbur, 1931-1937 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Day, Edmund E., 1931-1947 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Dodge, Raynaond, 1933-1942 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Dollard, John, 1933-1952 (Box 3, Folder 24-25)
    - Farrar and Rhinehart Incorporated Publishers, 1942-1945 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Federal Emergency Relief Administration, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Ferrin, Dana, 1931-1936 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Flint, Charles, 1926-1935 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Foreign Policy Association, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Gates, Arthur I., 1934-1952 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Givens, Willard E., 1935-1951 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Gorer, Geoffrey, 1936-1947 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Greulich, W. W., 1935-1953 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Guggenheim Foundation, 1937-1949 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Harcourt, Brace and Company, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Hartshorne, Hugh, 1924-1955 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Hill, Clyde M., 1937-1954 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Houghton Mifflin Company, 1942-1947 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Hull, Clark, 1929-1953 (Box 4, Folder 40-41)
    - Institute of Social and Religious Research, 1924-1934 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Lumsdaine, Arthur A, 1949-1960 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Lynd, Robert S., 1929-1945 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Malinowski, Bronislaw, 1940-1942, undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Mead, Margaret, 1936-1941 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Miller, Neal, 1936-1953 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Movrrer, O. Hobart, 1936-1958 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Murphy, Gardner, 1929-1945 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Murray, Henry, 1935-1941 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Stoeckel, Robbins Battell [mostly re: studies of motor vehicle drivers and social calls between May and Stoeckel]
      - 1929-1932 (Box 5, Folder 51)
      - 1933-1938 (Box 5, Folder 52)
      - 1940-1958 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Syracuse University, 1918-1949 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Terman, Lewis M., 1931-1951 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Union Theological Seminary, 1932-1934 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Wilson, Edwin B., 1930-1946 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Woodworth, R. S., 1931-1950 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Zook, George F., 1943-1950 (Box 5, Folder 59)
- Professional Files, 1914-1978; Series II
  This series consists of documentation concerning significant institutional settings of May's professional life and is organized into five sections: Biographical, Professional Organizations and Institutions, Teaching Materials, Union Theological Seminary, and Yale University. Each section is organized alphabetically. The first section, Biographical, includes curriculum vitae anda tribute to May by his nephew, William W. May. The tribute is a valuable summary of May's long professional career. The I second section documents affiliations with institutions and organizations, other than Yale University, which May maintained. The documents in this section are mostly routine correspondence. The Teaching Materials section contains lecture notes, course outlines, and assignments and exams for psychology courses taught by May. They are organized into two subsections: numbered and unnumbered courses. Many ofthese courses were taught by May in the Department of Psychology at Yale University. The Union Theological Seminary section primarily contains writings by May during his years ofstudying and teaching there. The Yale University section documents work at the university. The two "Department of Psychology" folders consist ofcorrespondence and minutes offaculty meetings. Most ofthese materials are not directly related to May, but they offer information about the department at mid-century. The Institute of Human Relations (IHR) materials are interesting but limited in quantity. An abstract ofsessions ofthe "Monday Night Group," IHR staff seminars held in the 1930s, details the broad intellectual concerns ofthe Institute. May's "Toward a Science of Human Behavior: A Survey of the Work of the Institute ofHuman Relations Through Two Decades, 1929-1949," offers an examination ofthe Institute, its stated goals, and its internal structure.
  - Biographical
    - General, 1957, 1978, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Graduate Exams, 1914, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Psychological Ethics [lecture notes for a course taken at Columbia University under John Dewey], undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - A Psychologist of Many Hats: A Tribute to Mark Arthur May" [by William W. May] (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Professional organizations and institutions
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1923, 1925 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Harvard University, 1946-1954 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - International Congress of Psychology [Ninth], 1929 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - The Psychological Corporation, 1937-1949 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Teaching Film Custodians, 1938-1966 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - United States School of Military Psychology, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Teaching materials
    - Numbered courses
      - Psychology 10a
        - 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 11)
        - 1960-1961, no date (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - Psychology 20, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - Psychology 21, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - Psychology 26a
        - Lecture notes, 1949-1951 (Box 6, Folder 15)
        - Course outline and assignments, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 16)
      - Psychology 30b, 1957, n.d (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - Psychology 90, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Unnumbered courses
      - The Psychology of Advertising and Selling, 1920, undated (Box 7, Folder 19)
      - Leadership, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 20)
      - The Psychology of Character Education, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
      - Science lecture, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 22)
      - Seminar on educational concepts, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Union Theological Seminary
    - Sermons, 1914-1915, undated (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Theology, 1915, undated (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Yale University
    - Angell, James Rowland [printed biographical materials], 1937, 1941, 1949, 1963, undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Department of Education [ph.D. alumni list], undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Department of Psychology, 1940-1968,. undated (Box 7, Folder 28-29)
    - Institute of Human Relations
      - Monday Night Group, 1938-1939 (Box 7, Folder 30)
      - Reports [from committees], 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 31)
      - Toward a Science of Human Behavior: A Survey of the Work ofthe Institute of Human Relations Through Two Decades, 1929-1949", 1950 (Box 7, Folder 32)
      - "Yale Interprets the News" [interview], 1950 (Box 7, Folder 33)
      - Miscellaneous, 1939, undated (Box 7, Folder 34)
- Research and Work, 1918-1965; Series III
  This series is organized alphabetically by topic. All of the documents relate to areas of research in which May was interested or involved, although they do not all pertain directly to work May himself carried out. Many of the materials collected in these folders constitute the research ofothers. Still, the series is representative of the range of research in which May was engaged. Several folders are devoted to the Character Education Inquiry, a highly regarded collaborative project undertaken early in Mays' career which sought to devise ways of assessing character and measuring attitudes in school children. In 1958, May was part of a team of scholars who visited the Soviet Union and he subsequently produced writings on Soviet psychology and education. This trip was connected to his work with the United States Advisory Commission on Information for which he made other trips abroad. The materials related to his work for the Commission include mostly reports of these trips which suggest the Commission's concerns with forging strong international links between the United States government and other countries. Documents pertaining to the Soviet Union trip are filed under Soviet Union while documents on the other trips are located under United States Advisory Commission on Information. Office of Scientific Research and Development (OSRD) documents, mostly correspondence and reports, concern research May undertook for the OSRD and the War Department, especially concerning the psychological damages in soldiers caused by the use of different weapons. The materials collected in "Motion pictures" suggest the prominent role May believed motion pictures would come to play in modem public education. "Magazine quizzes" contains various personality quizzes which May formulated for women's magazines in the 1940s.
  - Adolescence, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Advertising, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Air raid panic, 1941-1942 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Alpha and beta tests, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - American Institutes for Research [research proposal], 1965 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - American magazine poll, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Anticipatory response, 1940, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Anxiety, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Character Education Inquiry at Teacher's College, undated (Box 8, Folder 9-12)
  - Conscientious objectors, 1918 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Drives, 1942, 1945, undated (Box 8, Folder 14-15)
  - Interest Values Inventory, 1931, 1938, 1939, undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Learning experiments, 1945-1949 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Lewerenz-Steinmetz orientation test, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Magazine quizzes
    - Contracts, 1945-1949 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Redbook, 1945-1949 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous, 1943, undated (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Measurement of the change in attitudes on a four-point scale, undated (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Mental health tests, 1938, 1940, 1944-1946 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Minnesota Inventory of Social Behavior [and other personality scale tests], 1937, 1939, undated (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Motion pictures and schools, 1933-1939, undated (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Motion pictures, 1929-1930 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Office of Scientific Research and Development, 1944-1948, undated (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Paths of Life, undated (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Personality, 1929, undated (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Proposed test to discover responses to moral situations [notes], undated (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Readership studies
    - Liberty, 1941-1942, undated (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - True Story, undated (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Re-education in the healing arts [notes], undated (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Reinforcement, 1946, undated (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - Shock, undated (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - Social classes
    - Dominance, undated (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - Prestige, 1938-1939, undated (Box 10, Folder 37)
  - Soviet Union
    - Arrangements and correspondence, 1958-1960, undated (Box 10, Folder 38)
    - Notes on trip to Russia, 1957-1960, undated (Box 10, Folder 39)
    - Yale Reports [transcript ofradio program interview], 1959 (Box 10, Folder 40)
  - Syracuse University, undated (Box 10, Folder 41)
  - United States Advisory Commission on Information, 1949-1962 (Box 10, Folder 42-43)
  - Visual Education, 1945, undated (Box 10, Folder 44)
  - Youth
    - Christian Science Monitor [articles], 1935, undated (Box 10, Folder 45)
    - miscellaneous, 1934-1935 (Box 10, Folder 46)
  - Miscellaneous, 1959-1960, undated (Box 10, Folder 47)
- Writings, 1911-1971; Series IV
  This series is organized alphabetically by title. The type of writing ("article," "book chapter," or "speech") of each title is oftenunclear and it is difficult to determine for many of the titles whether they were published. The majority of the writings are from the decades May spent at Yale University where he was a professor of educational psychology and, later, director of the Institute of Human Relations (IHR). Some ofthe writings focus specifically on the aims and work ofthe lHR. May's ideas concerning the importance of education and its relation to the challenges of modern life are imparted throughout. Connected to this, May wrote on the struggles and cultural situation of Depression-era youth. The writings on education and youth demonstrate a concern with questions about how responsible national citizenries are formed. Many of the pieces detail May's considerable interest in the possibilities for social betterment offered by motion picture technology. In the speech "Educational Possibilities of Motion Pictures," May suggests that the motion picture is the most vital educational instrument of modem times due to its ability to convey facts and emotions without the "difficulties of language and limitations ofwords." May's perspectives on scientific knowledge as expressed in "Some Limitations of the Social Sciences" and other pieces evince his interest in the cultural constraints of science. At the end of the series there is one folder of book reviews written by May.
  - Adaptive Behavior, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - The Adult in the Community, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - The Automobile Age, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Basis for Determining Social Classes -U.S.A., undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - The Behavior of Social Scientists, 1940, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Challenge and Opportunity, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - The Challenge of the Present World Crisis to the American Eamily, 1941, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - The Challenge of the Present World Situation to Social Work, 1941 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Character Education: A Community Responsibility, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - The Church's Place in the Community, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - The Cold War, 1956 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - The Coming Peace, 1911 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Comparison of Schools and Classrooms with Respect to Honesty and Other Points, undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - A Comprehensive Plan for Measuring Personality, undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - The Concept of Personality in Contemporary Psychology, undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Cooperative Research, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Cooperative Research, Chapter m, undated (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Coordination of the Sciences of Behavior, 1940 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - A Description of Behavior Problems in Terms of Social Requirements, undated (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - The Dilemma of Youth, 1935 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Education: A Factor in National Recovery, 1933 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Education and a Science of Human Behavior, 1951 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Education and Society, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Education for the New Deal, undated (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Education for the Unemployed, 1933 (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Education in a World of Fear, 1940 (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - Education in an Anxious World, 1940, undated (Box 11, Folder 27-28)
  - The Education of a Democrat, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - Educational Opportunities for Youth, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 30)
  - Educational Opportunities in the Postwar Years, undated (Box 12, Folder 31)
  - Educational Possibilities of Motion Pictures, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 32)
  - Entertainment, Education, and Propaganda, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 33)
  - Eugenics and Education [author unknown], undated (Box 12, Folder 34)
  - The Evolution of Three Psychologies of Education, 1953 (Box 12, Folder 35)
  - An Experimental Approach to the Study of Character, 1932 (Box 12, Folder 36)
  - An Experimentally Acquired Drive, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 37)
  - Experimentally Acquired Drives, 1948 (Box 12, Folder 38)
  - Facts and Fiction about Bringing up Children, undated (Box 12, Folder 39)
  - Falling Short of the Democratic Ideals inEducation, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 40)
  - Family, undated (Box 12, Folder 41)
  - Films and Teaching Functions [correspondence only], 1945 (Box 12, Folder 42)
  - Films for World Democracy, undated (Box 12, Folder 43)
  - The Foundations of Personality, undated (Box 12, Folder 44)
  - The Frustrations of Modem Life, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 45)
  - The Glories of Football, undated (Box 12, Folder 46)
  - Goal-Gradient Hypothesis, 1941 (Box 12, Folder 47)
  - Guns, Dollars and Diplomacy From the Standpoint of International .Understanding [address to United States Department of Education], 1954 (Box 12, Folder 48)
  - The History of Imageless Thought, undated (Box 12, Folder 49)
  - How to Learn Better and Faster [correspondence only], 1951-1953 (Box 12, Folder 50)
  - Human Problems in Family Life, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 51)
  - The Inductive-Reductive Method in Social Research, 1940, undated (Box 12, Folder 52)
  - The Institute of Human Relations
    - The Institute of Human Relations, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 53)